Guide to the Robert Ensko Inc. Records 1787-1798, 1908-1978 (bulk 1934-1970) MS 200
New-York Historical Society
Robert Ensko Inc. records
1787-1798, 1908-1978 (bulk 1934-1970)
New-York Historical Society
Robert Ensko Inc.
MS 200
186.83 Linear feet in 187 boxes (bulk are record cartons)
The collection includes the extensive records of the Robert Ensko Inc. company, a New York City-based purveyor of antique and reproduction silver objects, from around the time of its incorporation in 1929 to the close of the business in 1970 shortly after the death of its principal, Stephen G.C. Ensko. The records include business correspondence, photographs of silver objects, inventories, client/customer sales tickets and other transaction records, invoices to Ensko from silversmiths, engravers, and other suppliers, and other documents.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in 5 series:
Series I. Correspondence (1796-1798, 1934-1970)
Series II. Photographs and Pictorial Works (1787, 1908-1971)
Series III. Inventories and Financial Records (1929-1978)
Series IV. Client Lists & Related Records (1937-1970)
Series V. Sales Tickets and Invoices (1941-1970)
Biographical / Historical
The firm Robert Ensko Inc. was a New York City-based purveyor, or retailer, of antique and reproduction British and American silver. The firm was incorporated in 1929 by its namesake and founder, Robert Ensko (1855-1934), and the present collection includes the records of the firm from that date of incorporation. But the firm pointed to 1878 as its founding year and Robert likely operated in a sole proprietorship capacity until 1929. Robert was well-known in the trade as the author of an important reference work, "Makers of American Silver," published in 1915. The firm was located at 682 Lexington Avenue in Manhattan.
At the time of incorporation in 1929, Robert continued as president of the firm, with his son Stephen G.C. (Guernsey Cook) Ensko as treasurer and a nephew, Charles Ensko, as secretary. Charles would retire and Robert would die soon after the firm's incorporation. Stephen (1896-1969), along with his brother, Lamont, remained as principal of the firm until his death. Stephen established himself as an authority on silver, authoring the first edition of "American Silversmiths and Their Marks" in 1927 and "English Silver 1675–1825" in 8 volumes, with Edward Wenham.
Stephen married Dorothea J. Winterloff (1892–1977) in 1918. They had three children, including Dorothea Charlotte (1920–2014), the donor of the collection to New-York Historical. Dorothea Charlotte married Vernon C. Wyle in 1944; Wyle was active in the family business for at least a time. After Stephen's death in December 1969, the firm continued business for a few months, but closed in 1970. The inventory was distributed to an extent among the family, with the rest auctioned.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Stephen G.C. Ensko's daughter, Dorothea (Dee) Charlotte Wyle, in 1991, with a small addition from Wyle in 2003.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes the records of the Robert Ensko Inc. company from around the time of its incorporation in 1929 to the close of the business in 1970. The records are particularly strong in documenting the firm's transactions with its clients/customers. The related records include correspondence, order tickets, invoices, shipping and contact lists, index cards of client transaction data, client "has and wants" lists, and ledgers. An especially notable client represented extensively in the records is the New York Racing Association, for which Ensko was the provider of trophies and other awards for races at Aqueduct, Belmont, and Saratoga from at least the late 1950s through 1970. The New York Yacht Club and Yale University are among the many other organizations that purchased silver presentation objects from Ensko.
Also well-represented in the collection are records relating to Ensko's transactions with its providers of antique and reproduction silver and engraving, and Ensko's inventory of objects. These records include invoices (bills paid) from the suppliers to Ensko, stock purchase journals, index cards of object-level data, correspondence with dealers, inventory catalogues, and the like.
Other records include correspondence concerning inquiries from museum curators, researchers and others about historical silversmiths; correspondence concerning appraisals of holdings by estates and others of silver objects, with some related inventories; photographs (prints and negatives) of silver objects; research and reference notes on silversmiths; tax filings; general business expenses; and other material.
Inventories, Retail -- New York (State) -- New York.; Selling -- Silverwork -- New York (State) -- New York.; Silverwork -- Collectors and collecting.; Silverwork -- Reproduction.; Accounts.; Invoices.; Letters (correspondence); Photographs.; Research notes.; Sales records.; Ensko, Stephen Guernsey Cook, 1896-1969; New York Racing Association; New York Yacht Club; Yale University
- Series I. Correspondence, 1796-1798, 1934-1970; 39.33 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes both incoming and outgoing business correspondence of Robert Ensko Inc. The correspondents include individual collectors/purchasers, museum curators, historical researchers, appraisers, engravers, silversmiths, dealers and other suppliers, and university, association, and other institutional purchasers of silver objects. Among the more frequent institutional clients appearing in these files are various units of Yale University and the New York Racing Association, which purchased trophies from Ensko beginning in the late 1950s (and perhaps earlier) for races at Aqueduct, Belmont, and Saratoga.
  The subject matter of the correspondence perhaps mostly concerns clients or potential clients seeking particular antique silver objects or reproductions of such objects. Requests for engraving are also common. Drawings and some photographs are found in the files as patrons described their objectives to Ensko. Ensko maintained relationships over the years with their individual clients and with their supply chain of dealers, engravers and silversmiths to satisfy client wishes, and so the correspondence reflects the ongoing development of silver collections through Ensko. The correspondence appears to be largely complete, running from 1936 (with a few letters back to 1934) through to the firm's close in 1970.
  In addition to documentation of purchases and other business transactions, the correspondence includes other matters that Ensko assisted with, including answering historical research questions from independent historians, such as Helen Burr Smith, and curators at Albany Institute of History and Art, Detroit Institute of Arts, Yale University Art Gallery of Fine Art, and elsewhere. Ensko also was called on to offer both informal appraisals of objects and more formal appraisals of silver holdings in collections and estates; the appraised inventories are found at various points throughout the files. Ensko also occasionally loaned objects for exhibition at museums and elsewhere and that is documented in these files.
  The files also include some personal correspondence at points, and correspondence with the firm's attorneys and accountants that run on the border of personal and professional. The set of correspondence for January-June 1936 includes letters from the Smithsonian concerning British assay office receipts; six receipts dated 1796-98 were enclosed for Stephen Ensko to keep and these are in the files as reflected in the series' date range.
  Arrangement
  The series retains its original order, which includes multiple sets of letters arranged alphabetically by correspondent. The sets advance in rough chronological order from the 1930s to 1970. There is a fair amount of inconsistency though in the files. In terms of chronology, some sets consist entirely of letters from one particular year, while others include letters from a wider range of time. More uneven is how correspondents, especially those from institutions, were filed in the alphabetical sequence. For example, correspondence with Yale University representatives can be found under Y, or under the letter of the individual correspondent, such as P for John M. Phillips or S for Theodore Sizer. Dealers with personal names in their firm name, such as I. Freeman and Son, will typically be found under the surname (F), not the lead letter of the company. These too might be found under a personal name, for example, the dealer Polly's Shop is found under P and under E for the proprietor, Polly Edwards. There are likely other idiosyncrasies not observed during processing; accordingly, patrons should be sure not to tailor their search in the files too narrowly.
  - Correspondence, 1796-1798, 1934-1939 (Offsite-box 59)
    Includes the sets of general correspondence for January-June 1936 and July-December 1936, and the set of correspondence (1936-1939) related to orders of "American Silversmiths and Their Marks II," with acknowledgements from libraries and others of donated copies from Ensko. The set of correspondence for January-June 1936 includes letters from the Smithsonian concerning British assay office receipts; six receipts dated 1796-98 were enclosed for Stephen Ensko to keep.
  - Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Offsite-box 5)
    The correspondence for 1937 to roughly the first half of 1939 was found in somewhat disordered state when processed in 2021. It appears likely that the correspondence was originally in three sets: much of 1937, then late 1937 into 1938, and then 1938 into mid-1939. The correspondence was given a rough sort in 2021 into two sets: 1937-38 and 1939. This box includes correspondents A-I for 1937-38.
  - Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Offsite-box 6)
    Includes correspondents J-Z for 1937-38.
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Offsite-box 10)
    Includes correspondents A-Z for 1939, but it appears that the correspondence is only from the first six to nine months or so of the year.
  - Correspondence (RESTRICTED), circa 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 49)
    RESTRICTED: These files require conservation vacuum treatment before they can be used. The box holds a set of correspondence files, which because of their condition were not closely inspected, but they appear to include letters from 1939 and likely are the continuation of the above letters of 1939 and into early 1940.
  - Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Offsite-box 60)
    Includes four sets of correspondence with somewhat overlapping date ranges and correspondents, running from early 1940 to mid-1941.
  - Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Offsite-box 61)
    Includes three sets of correspondence ranging from about mid-1941 to early 1942.
  - Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Offsite-box 62)
    Includes two sets of correspondence, one covering most of 1942 and the other from late 1942 to mid-1943.
  - Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Offsite-box 63)
    Includes three sets of correspondence ranging roughly from mid-1943 to mid-1944.
  - Correspondence, 1944-1945 (Offsite-box 64)
    Includes three sets of correspondence ranging roughly from mid-1944 to mid-1945.
  - Correspondence, 1945-1946 (Offsite-box 65)
    Includes three sets of correspondence that run roughly from mid 1945 to mid-1946.
  - Correspondence, 1946-1951 (Offsite-box 7)
    Includes two sets of correspondence completing 1946, ranging roughly from mid-1946 to the end of the year. Then the box begins what appears to be the combination of several sets of correspondence that range from 1947 through 1950, with some 1951; this box holds correspondents A-B.
  - Correspondence, 1947-1951 (Offsite-box 8)
    This box continues the sets of correspondence for the years from 1947-1950, with some into 1951; includes correspondents C-G. There is then a gap for correspondents H-S, which does not seem to be in the collection. (The boxes with correspondence files for 1957 include some files that range back to the 1940s, but do not cover all the missing documents.)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1951 (Offsite-box 11)
    This box continues the sets of correspondence for the years from 1947-1950, with some into 1951; includes correspondents T-Z.
  - Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Offsite-box 28)
    Correspondents A-L
  - Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Offsite-box 29)
    Correspondents M-Z
  - Correspondence. Queen Anne pattern orders (Box 1 of 2), 1950-1953 (Offsite-box 38)
    This box and the next include only orders for reproduction Queen Anne Pattern, English silver-plated (S.P.) flatware. This box has correspondents A-J, the next has K-Z.
  - Correspondence. Queen Anne pattern orders (Box 2 of 2), 1950-1953 (Offsite-box 39)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1954 (Offsite-box 186)
    Correspondents A-G, M
  - Correspondence, 1952-1954 (Offsite-box 187)
    Correspondents P-Z
  - Correspondence, 1955 (Offsite-box 30)
    Correspondents A-R
  - Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Offsite-box 31)
    Correspondents S-Z (1955) and A-L (1956).
  - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Offsite-box 32)
    Correspondents M-Z (1956) and A-B (1957). The 1957 files include some multi-year files that range from the 1940s to 1957.
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Offsite-box 33)
    Includes correspondents B-L. Though the files primarily date from 1957, there are some multi-year files that range from the 1940s to 1957.
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Offsite-box 34)
    Includes correspondents M-Z. Though the files primarily date from 1957, there are some multi-year files that range from the 1940s to 1957.
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Offsite-box 35)
    Includes correspondents A-R, including New York Racing Association (NYRA)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Offsite-box 36)
    Includes correspondents S-Z (1958) and A-H (1959).
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Offsite-box 37)
    Includes correspondents I-Z, including New York Racing Association (NYRA)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Offsite-box 22)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Offsite-box 23)
    Correspondents M-Z, including New York Racing Association (NYRA)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Offsite-box 19)
    Correspondents A-M
  - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Offsite-box 20)
    Correspondents N-Z (1961), including New York Racing Association (NYRA) and A-D (1962)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Offsite-box 21)
    Correspondents E-Z, including New York Racing Association (NYRA)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Offsite-box 16)
    Correspondents A-N, including New York Racing Association (NYRA)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Offsite-box 17)
    Correspondents O-Z (1963) and A-D (1964), including New York Racing Association (NYRA)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Offsite-box 18)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Offsite-box 13)
    Correspondents A-Z, including New York Racing Association (NYRA)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Offsite-box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Offsite-box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Offsite-box 15)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 40)
    Includes correspondents A-N, including New York Racing Association (NYRA)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 41)
    Includes correspondents O-Z. Also includes excise tax and other form filings for various individuals and organizations.
- Series II. Photographs and Pictorial Works, 1787, 1908-1971 (bulk 1950s-1960s); 12 Linear feet
  The series includes photographic prints and negatives of a wide variety of silver objects. Several albums include photos of trophies, with information about them, supplied by Robert Ensko Inc. to the New York Racing Association (NYRA) for "Run of the Mill" and "Stake" races at Aqueduct, Belmont and Saratoga in 1960-1966. There is also a set of three albums with photos (and a small box of negatives) of the Firestone Collection, which according to a note in the albums was appraised by Stephen G.C. Ensko.
  Beyond these albums, there are many other photographs, though their particular context is not clear. A large set of organized photograph files, originally in filing cabinets when received at N-YHS, seem likely to be mostly of objects that were in Ensko's inventory or of at least specific relevance to their business. These files include both photographic prints and negatives. They include both antiques and reproductions of styles designated on some folder labels as "English silver," "Sheffield," "antique English," "early American" (often abbreviated as E.A.), and "modern." The photos remain in their original folders with Ensko's labeling. Objects include trays, creamers, bowls, candlesticks, cups, coffee and tea sets, dishes, urns, strainers, porringers, tankards, shakers, sauce boats, flatware, Apostle spoons, etc. A separate set of several small boxes of negatives seem likely to relate to images of Ensko's inventory as well.
  Retained in their original flat letter boxes as received at N-YHS are various photographs and other image formats that appear to be more research or reference-oriented, such as for Ensko's books, appraisals, client inquiries, etc. The content of these letter boxes were not closely examined by the processing archivist in 2021 and were left largely as found in the boxes. While much is simply loosely piled in the boxes, there are discernable relationships among some of the grouped photographs, such as maker, style, marks, collection, etc. These materials include annotations, brief notes, and other documentation. A few unrelated items, such as personal notes, a 1918 wedding invitation, and a 1787 newspaper, are found randomly among these documents.
  Finally, there are three boxes of pictorial works, including bound copies of tearsheets of advertisements and articles about silver, a few museum exhibition and auction catalogues, booklets, postcards, and the like. Specific to Ensko are two copies of a small booklet published in 1934 by the firm that seems to be a primer on antique American silver for its clients or potential clients.
  The series is arranged with photographs followed by pictorial material. Within photographs the arrangement follows the degree to which the material is organized coherently, from most-organized (albums) to least.
  Some photographs can also be found in the inventories series of the collection and, to a limited extent, within the correspondence files.
  - Photograph albums: New York Racing Association, 1960-1963 (Offsite-box 66)
    The box holds 5 albums, all concerning the New York Racing Association, one each for 1960 and 1961, two for 1962 (with similar but not identical content), and one for 1963 (a second similar album for 1963 is in the next box). Each album is noted as including information lists and photos of trophies selected for "Run of the Mill" and "Stake" races for Aqueduct, Belmont, and Saratoga.
  - Photograph albums: New York Racing Association, 1963-1966 (Offsite-box 67)
    The box holds 6 albums, all concerning the New York Racing Association: 1963 (one album, perhaps identical, to the 1963 album in the preceding box); 1964 (one album for Run of the Mill and Stake for Aqueduct, Belmont, and Saratoga); one for 1965 Stake; one undated but likely 1965 for Run of the Mill; and 2 boxed albums for 1966, one for Run of the Mill, the other for Stake.
  - Photograph albums: Firestone Collection, undated (Offsite-box 70)
    3 albums of photos, apparently in connection with an appraisal of the collection performed by Stephen Ensko. Oversize flat box.
  - Photograph files of antique and reproduction silver (Box 1 of 4), 1950s-1960s (Offsite-box 1)
    This box includes several folders of photographs of objects related to the New York Racing Association (NYRA), including Belmont bowls, permanent trophies, and many others. There is also one folder of many photographs labeled "silver working." This box holds mostly prints with some negatives.
  - Photograph files of antique and reproduction silver (Box 2 of 4), 1950s-1960s (Offsite-box 2)
    This holds holds almost entirely negatives of objects.
  - Photograph files of antique and reproduction silver (Box 3 of 4), 1950s-1960s (Offsite-box 3)
    This box includes mostly prints, but with several negatives. Most folders seem to be labeled as "antique." One folder includes photographs of a John Coddington tankard owned by Robert G. Goelet.
  - Photograph files of antique and reproduction silver (Box 4 of 4), 1950s-1960s (Offsite-box 4)
    This box holds a mix of prints and negatives. It includes a folder of photographs of Apostle spoons.
  - Various photographs, 1787, undated (Offsite-box 68)
    This box holds: 1 and 2) two flat letter boxes with photos, negatives, and some notes regarding silversmiths and silver objects. The second box holds an original 1787 copy of the Massachusetts Sentinel of June 30, 1787 (number 30 of Volume VII) and a 1918 invoice to Steve Ensko; 3) a small box of negatives of the Firestone collection; and 4) a small box of slides of silver objects.
  - Various photographs, 1908-circa 1948, undated (Offsite-box 69)
    This box holds: 1) flat letter box of photos, negatives, etc. regarding silver objects and silversmiths. A few letters in the box are dated from 1908-1948. There are a small number of personal family letters from the 1930s and Stephen Ensko's 1918 wedding invitation mixed with the research notes; 2-8) small boxes of negatives labeled "Ensko" and running from number 1-844, with a gap; 9) one small box of negatives, unlabeled and possibly the gap from the preceding set; 10) small box of negatives labeled as NYRA 1970 trophies; and envelopes of postcards with photographs of silver objects.
  - Bound articles and advertisements (Box 1 of 2), 1920s-1960s (Offsite-box 71)
    This box and the next include ten bound volumes of articles and advertisements, typically illustrated, cut from magazines. The magazines Antiques and Connoisseur appear to be the most common, with International Studio and Antiquarian also appearing, possibly with others. Not all pages are dated, but those that are range from the 1920s to the 1960s, though the bulk appear to be from the 1950s-60s. In this box there is an additional bound volume that includes the cumulative indexes to Antiques for 1922-1956 (volumes I-LXX).
  - Bound articles and advertisements (Box 2 of 2), 1920s-1960s (Offsite-box 72)
  - Catalogues and other, circa 1927-1971 (Offsite-box 9)